Guide to the Carl von Marr Papers, 1874-1949
Department of Special Collections
Carl von Marr Papers,
1874-1949
Marr,Carl von
.5 linear ft. (ca.145 items).
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Marr was a well known painter in Munich where he held a chair at the Academy of Arts (Akademie der Kunste) from 1893 on, and later became its Director. He was born in Milwaukee, Wisonsin, in 1858, and died in Munich, Germany, 1936. He was tutored by Wisconsin artist Henry Vianden in Milwaukee from age 7 to 17, then he attended art schools in Weimer, Berlin, and Munich, where he took up residence as a painter.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, Stargardt auction, item 584, 1979
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bartels, Hans von, 1856-1913.; Becker-Gundahl, Carl Johann, 1856-1925.; Bermann, Cipri Adolf, 1862-.; Beronco, Hierl.; Blaas, Julius von, 1845-1922.; Blau-Lang, Tina, 1845-.; Blos, Carl, 1860-1941.; Borchardt, Hans, 1865-.; Bracht, Eugen Felix Prosper, 1842-1921.; Brhutt, Ferdinand, 1849-1936.; Dhurck-Kaulbach, J.; Fink, Bruno.; Fink, Selma.; Habermann, Hugo Freiherr von, 1849-1929.; Hanfstaegl, Kittie.; Hayek, Hans von, 1869-1940.; Heine, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1845-1921.; Hengeler, Adolf, 1863-.; Herterich, Ludwig, 1856-1932.; Hildebrand, Adolf von, 1847-1921.; Hoffmann, A.; Jank, Angelo, 1868-1940.; Kalckreuth, Leopold Karl Walter Graf von, 1855-1928.; Kampf, Arthur, 1864-1950.; Keller, Albert von, 1844-1920.; Knote, Ellen.; Koner, Max Johann Bernhard, 1854-1900.; Krilmleise, Wilheim.; Lenbach, Franz Seraph von, 1836-1904.; Lenbach, Lolo.; Liebermann, Max, 1847-1935.; Messerschmidt, Pius Ferdinand, 1858-1915.; Meyer, Claus, 1856-1919.; Meyer-Waldeck, Kunz, 1859-1953.; Meyerheim, Paul Friedrich, 1842-1915.; Miller, Ferdinand (II) von, 1842-1929.; Miller, Fritz von, 1840-1921.; Mhunzer, Adolf, 1870-1952.; Myrbach-Rheinfeld, Felician, 1853-.; Rehder, Julius Christian, 1861-.; Reinicke, Rene, 1860-1926.; Richter, Gustav Karl Ludwig, 1823-1884.; Rietschel, Ernest Friedrich August, 1804-1861.; Samberger, Leo, 1861-1949.; Schlereth, Hans, 1897-.; Schwill, William Valentine, 1864-.; Seidl, Emanuel von, 1856-1919.; Souchan, Wilhelm Ferdinand, 1825-1876.; Spier, Anna.; Stadler, Anton von, 1850-1917.; Stahl, Friedrich, 1863-1940.; Stieler, Eugene von, 1845-1929.; Stuck, Franz von, 1863-1928.; Stuck, Mary.; Taschner, Ignatius, 1871-1913.; Thiersch, Friedrich von, 1852-1921.; Thhony, Eduard, 1866-1950.; Trhubner, Wilhelm (Heinrich W.), 1851-1917.; Uhde, Fritz (Friedrich Karl Hermann) von, 1848-1911.; Urban, Hermann, 1866-.; Vogeler, Heinrich JOhann, 1872-1942.; Werner, Anton Alexander von, 1843-1915.; Woermann, K.; Zemberg, O.; Zhugel, Heinrich von, 1850-1941.; Art, Modern--20th century--Germany.; Art, Modern--19th century--Germany.; Art, German--History.; Munich (Germany).
Biographical Note
Born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin in 1858, Carl Marr was tutoted by Wisconsin artist Henry Vianden in Milwaukee from ages 7 through 17, after which he attended art schools in Weimar, Berlin and Munich, where he took up residence as a painter. He was appointed to a professorship in the Academy of Arts [Akademie der Kunste] in Munich in 1893 and later to its directorship. He died in Munich, Germany, in 1936.
Scope and Content
Ca. 145 items of incoming correspondence, most of it addressed to Carl Marr, a small portion addressed to his sister Selma Marr and her husband Bruno Fink. Most of the letters are from other painters and artists. Arranged alphabetically by sender.
Container List
- Bartels, Hans von (1856-1913) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  ALS, 1p., Oct. 11, 1898. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, Oct. 12, 1999. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 1p., April 18, 1902. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 1p., Nov. 18, 1907. To Carl Marr.
  (S-584)
- Becker-Gundahl, Carl Johann (1856-1925) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  ACS, n.d., to [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., n.d. To Carl Marr.
- Bermann, Cipri Adolf (b.1862) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  ACS, Nov. 4, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 3pp., n.d., To [Carl Marr].
- [Beronco, Hierl] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  ALS, 1p., May 24, 1908. To Carl Marr.
- Blass, Julius von (1845-1922) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  ALS, 3pp., Aug. 11, 1906. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 3pp., Aug. 28, 1906. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 2pp., March 18, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
- Blau-Lang, Tina (b.1845) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  ACS, April 11, 1899. To Mrs. B.E. Fink.
  ACS, n.d. to [P.F.] Messerschmitt.
- Blos, Carl (1860-1941) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  ALS, 3pp., Dec. 1, 1920. To Carl Marr.
- Bocker, Conrad (Box 1, Folder 8)
  ALS, 2pp., Oct. 31, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
- Borchardt, Hans (b.1865) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  ALS, 1p., Nov. 6, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
- Bracht, Eugen Felix Prosper (1842-1921) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  ALS, 1p., April 6, 1900. To [Carl Marr].
- Brütt, Ferdinand (1849-1936). (Box 1, Folder 11)
  ALS, 2pp., Aug. 7, 1906. To [Carl Marr].
- Dürck-Kaulbach, J. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  ALS, 3pp., July 24, 1919. To Carl Marr.
- Habermann, Hugo Freiherr (1849-1929). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  ALS, 2pp., Aug. 15, 1905. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, Sept. 25, 1905. To Carl Marr.
  ACS, Sept. 6, 1909. To Carl Marr.
  ACS, Sept. 1, 1918. To Carl Marr.
  ACS, Sept. 15, 1920. To Carl Marr.
  ACS, n.d. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 1pp., n.d. To Carl Marr.
- Hanfstaengl, Kittie. (wife of Franz Seraph H.) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  ALS, 4pp., March 17, 1900. To Bruno Fink.
  ALS, 4pp., June 19, 1900. To Bruno Fink.
  ALS, 4pp., July 9, 1900. To Bruno Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., n.d. To [Mrs. Bruno Fink].
- Hayek, Hans von (1869-1940) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  ALS, 2pp., Nov. 5, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
- Heine, Friedrich Wilhelm (1845-1921). (Box 1, Folder 16)
  ALS, 1p., Dec. 11, 190[6]. To Mrs. Bruno Fink.
- Hengeler, Adolf (b. 1863) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  ALS, 1p., March 30, 1902. To Carl Marr.
  ACS, Jan. 19, 1903. To Carl Marr
  ACS, Jan. 7, 1907. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., April 3, 1910. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, Jan. 2, 1911. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, Jan. 31, 1917. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, Nov. 24, 1919. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, Nov. 25, n.d., To [Carl Marr].
- Herterich, Ludwig (1856-1932). (Box 1, Folder 18)
  ALS, 2pp., July 29, 1905. To Carl Marr.
- Hildebrand, Adolf von (1847-1932). (Box 1, Folder 19)
  ALS, 2pp., Jan. 12, 1911. To Carl Marr.
- Hoffmann, A. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  ALS, 3pp., Jan. 14, 1911. To [Carl Marr].
- Jank, Angelo (1868-1940). (Box 1, Folder 21)
  ACS, Jan. 2, 1907. To Carl Marr.
  ACS, Feb. 3, 1928. To Carl Marr.
- Kalckreuth, Leopold Karl Walter V. (1855-1928). (Box 1, Folder 22)
  ALS, 2pp., Nov. 21, 1905. To [Carl Marr].
  (2-584)
- Kampf, Arthur (1864-1950). (Box 1, Folder 23)
  ALS, 2pp., Nov. 5, 1908. To Carl Marr.
- Keller, Albert von (1844-1920). (Box 1, Folder 24)
  3 letters to Marr. 1905, 1907, 1919.
- Knote, Ellen. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Letter to Marr, [1907].
- Koner, Max Johann Bernhard (1854-1900). (Box 1, Folder 26)
  ALS, 2pp., April 5, 1900. To Carl Marr.
- Krilmleise, Willi. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  ALS, 4pp., Jan. 3, 1914. To Carl Marr.
- Lenbach, Franz Seraph v. (1836-1904). (Box 1, Folder 28)
  LS, 1p., March 15, 1901. To [Carl Marr].
  ACS, n.d. To [Carl Marr].
- Lenbach, Lolo (wife of Franz Seraph v. L.) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  ALS, 1p., Oct. 30, 1901. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 4pp., n.d. To Carl Marr.
- Liebermann, Max (1847-1935) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  TLS, 1p., Sept. 7, 1928. To Carl Marr.
- Marr, Carl v. (1858-1936). (Box 1, Folder 31)
  ALS, 1p., Aug. 21, 1900. To Bruno Fink.
- Messerschmitt, Pius Ferdinand (1858-1915). (Box 1, Folder 32)
  ACS, July 4, 1900. To Bruno Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Aug. 9, 1901. To Bruno Fink.
- Meyer, Claus (1856-1919). (Box 1, Folder 33)
  ALS, 2pp., March 9, 1901. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 4pp., Feb. 25, 1902. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 3pp., Feb. 12, 1907. To [Carl Marr].
- Meyerheim, Paul Friedrich (1842-1915). (Box 1, Folder 34)
  ALS, 1p., April 29, 1876. To Hochgeehrter Herr.
  ALS, 1/2p., Sept. 11, 1894. Top half of p. missing.
  (S-662)
  ALS, 1p., April 14, 1905. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 3pp., Feb. 28, 1907. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 3pp., June 8, 1907. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 2pp., July 7, 1907. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 4pp., July 10, 1907. To Carl Marr.
- Meyer-Waldeck, Kunz (1859-1953). (Box 1, Folder 35)
  ALS, 4pp., Jan. 22, 1910. To Bruno Fink.
  ALS, 3pp., Sept. 7, 1932. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Dec. 29, 1932. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 1p., Feb. 19, 1935. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Feb. 19, 1935. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Feb. 2, 1936. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., June 28, 1936. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 4pp., Nov. 1, 1936. To Mrs. Fink.
  ALS, 4pp., Sept. 1, 1937. To Mrs. Fink.
  AMs, 4pp., n.d. Abschied von Friedr. H. Hinze [by Meyer Waldeck's father].
- Miller, Ferdinand (II) v. (1842-1929). (Box 1, Folder 36)
  ACS, Aug. 7, 1905. To Carl Marr.
- Miller, Fritz v. (1840-1921). (Box 1, Folder 37)
  ALS, 3pp., Jan. 4, 1911. To [Carl Marr].
- Münzer, Adolf (1870-1952). (Box 1, Folder 38)
  ALS, 1p., Nov. 7, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., Nov. 14, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., June 13, 1909. To [Carl Marr].
- [Myrbach-Rheinfeld, Felician (b.1853)] (Box 1, Folder 39)
  ALS, 1p., July 21, 1902. To [Carl Marr].
- Rehder, Julius Christian (b.1861). (Box 1, Folder 40)
  ALS, 1p., Sept. 13, 1944. To Selma Fink.
- Reinicke, René (1860-1926). (Box 1, Folder 41)
  ACS, April 4, 1910. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 2pp., July 11, 1921. To Schr geehrter Herr.
  ACS, July 12, 1921. To business manager of Munich's Artists' Guild.
- Richter, Gustav Karl Ludwig (1823-84). (Box 1, Folder 42)
  ALS, 2pp., n.d. To verehrtester Freund.
- Rietschel, ERnst Friedrich (1804-61). (Box 1, Folder 43)
  ACS, n.d.
- Samberger, Leo (1861-1949). (Box 1, Folder 44)
  ALS, 3pp., Nov. 3, 1908. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 2pp., Nov. 6, 19[0]8. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 2pp., Nov. 8, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., March 12, 1909. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 2pp., n.d. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 2pp., n.d. To Carl Marr.
- Schlereth, Hans (b.1897). (Box 1, Folder 45)
  ALS, 4pp., March 11, 1936. To Selma Marr-Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., April 20, 1936. To Selma Marr-Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Oct. 30, 1936. To Selma Marr-Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Nov. 30, 1936. To Selma Marr-Fink.
  ALS, 3pp., Nov. 1, 1937. To Selma Marr-Fink.
  ALS, 2pp., Feb. 3, 1938. To Selma Marr-Fink.
- Schwill, William Valentine (b.1864). (Box 1, Folder 46)
  ALS, 2pp., July 12, 1936. To Janet M. Peck.
  ALS, 2pp., enclosed with letter above. From Janet P[eck] to Jane.
  ALS, 2pp., Aug. 7, 1936. To Mrs. Bruno Fink.
- Seidl, Emanuel v (1856-1919). (Box 1, Folder 47)
  ALS, 1p., April 4, [1899]. To [Carl Marr].
- Spier, Anna. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  ACS, Nov. 30, 1900. To Mutter des ausgezeichneten Kunstlers.
- Stadler, Anton v. (1850-1917). (Box 1, Folder 49)
  ALS, 1p., Oct. 29, 1906. To Carl Marr.
- Stahl, Friedrich (1863-1940) (Box 1, Folder 50)
  ALS, 2 pp., Jan 18, 1911. To Carl Marr.
- Stieler, Eugene v. (1845-1929) (Box 1, Folder 51)
  ALS, 1p., Oct. 5, 1907. To Carl Marr.
- Stuck, Franz v. (1863-1928). (Box 1, Folder 52)
  ALS, 2pp., Oct. 8, 1900. To Schrgeehrter Herr.
  (S-591)
  AC, Dec. 15, 19[0]5. To Carl Marr.
  LS, 2pp., Sept. 30, 1923. To Carl Marr.
  LS, 4pp., Oct. 20, 1927. To [Carl Marr].
- Stuck, Mary. (Wife of Franz v.S.) (Box 1, Folder 53)
  ALS, 2pp., Feb. 8, 1901. To Carl Marr.
- Taschner, Ignatius (1871-1913). (Box 1, Folder 54)
  ALS, 4pp., Aug. 7, 190[6]. To Carl Marr.
- Thiersch, Friedrich v. (1852-1921) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  ALS, 3pp., June 19, 1900. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., Nov. 18, 1920. To [Carl Marr].
  (S584)
- Thöny, Edward (1866-1950). (Box 1, Folder 56)
  ALS, 2pp., Oct. 29, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
- Trübner, Wilhelm (1851-1917). (Box 1, Folder 57)
  ALS, 1p., Dec. 6, 1908. To Carl Marr.
- Uhde, Friedrich Karl Hermann v. (1848-1911). (Box 1, Folder 58)
  ACS, Jan. 22, 1876. To Baron v. Loen.
  ALS, 1p., April 13, 1897. To Kunz Meyer.
  LS, 1p., June 26, 1902. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 1p., Nov. 5, 1908. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 1p., Aug. 4, 1909. To Carl Marr.
- Urban, Hermann (b.1866). (Box 1, Folder 59)
  ALS, 2pp., June 2, 1914. To M. Fink.
  ACS, June 24, 1914. To Fink.
  ACS, n.d., To Carl Marr.
- Vogeler, Heinrich Johann (1872-1942). (Box 1, Folder 60)
  ALS, 1p., Feb. 9, 1910. To Carl Marr.
- Werner, Anton Alexander v. (1843-1915). (Box 1, Folder 61)
  ALS, 1p., April 19, 1874. To Konig.
  (S-536)
  ALS, 3pp., Feb. 17, 1893. To Carl Marr.
  AL, 3pp., Feb. 24, 1893. To Carl Marr.
  ALS, 2pp., March 23, 1896. To [I.] M. Magnus.
  See also M287/2/1
- Woermann, K. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  ALS, 2pp., May 8, 1907. To Carl Marr.
- Zemberg, O. (Box 1, Folder 63)
  ALS, 1p., April 19, 1900. To [Carl Marr].
- Zügel, Heinrich v. (1850-1941). (Box 1, Folder 64)
  ALS, 4pp., May 19, 1917. To [Carl Marr].
  ALS, 2pp., Oct. 28, 1935. To Carl Marr.
- Unidentified senders. (Box 1, Folder 65)
  AL, 1p., Dec. 9, 1909. To [Carl Marr]. Stationery letterhead; K.B. Direction der staatlichen galerien.
  Alte Pinakothek, Munchen.
  TLS, 1p., April 19, 1922. To Carl Marr. Stationery letterhead: Syndikat der bayrischen Akademie der bildenden Kunste.